A Guide to the Black Newspaper Collection
Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Black Newspapers Collection 1882-1913
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
1976-55d
An artificial collection made by VSU Special Collections
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
African American Newspapers
Newspapers are a rich source for investigating the social, political, and economic activities in a community. African American Newspapers unlike their European American counterparts, they offer a unique insight into avenues often neglected by European American Publications.
Scope and Content Information
Political and Social activities, church news, ads, editorials from an African American perspective. African American newspapers have traditionally tried to fill in the information gap created by the majority news system. These papers provide a unique view of this perspective.
There are some additional copies of Africian American newspapers located in the following manuscript groups: 1. James Hugo Johnston, Sr. Acc. # 1963-9 2. James Hugo Johnston, Jr. Acc. # 1963-10 3. Edna Meade Colson Acc. # 1965-13
Contents List
- 1882-1913
  - The Colored Virginian- Petersburg, Va Oct 5 1912, June 7 1913 (Volume 1:1)
    Frequency: Weekly, Editor: Arthur B. Mackey
  - The Richmond Planet- Richmond, Va July 12, 1890 (Volume 1:2)
    Frequency: Weekly, Owner: John Mitchell, Jr.
  - The Reformer- Richmond, Va Sept 20,1902 (Volume 1:3)
    Frequency: Undertermined, Publisher: The Grand Fountain
  - The Recorder-Petersburg,Va May 20, 1893 (Volume 1:4)
    Frequency: Weekly, President: William H. Major
  - The Freeman- Indianapolis, Indiana Dec 25,1897 (Volume 1:5)
    Frequency: Weekly, Editor: George L. Knox
  - The Virginia Lancet-Petersburg,Va Jan 14,1888 (Volume 1:6)
    Frequency: Undetermined, Editor:W.W. Evans
  - The Lancet- Petersburg,Va Jan-March 1985 (Volume 1:7)
    Frequency: Weekly, Editor: Rev.Mr. George Freeman Bragg
  - The Lancet-Petersburg,Va Feb and March 1883, Dec 13, 1884 (Volume 1:8)
  - The African Nationalist-Liberia, W Africa, The Negro Sporting News-Washington DC, Color Flash-Charleston,W Va May 1 1943, April 1 1945, May 1945 (Volume 1:9)
    Frequency:Weekly Editor:C.Frederick Taylor, Frequency:Bi-Weekly Editor: Andrew F. Jackson, Frequency: Monthly Editor:I.J.K wells
  - The Basptist Pilot-Winton, NC Aug 13 1889 (Volume 1:10)
    Frequency: Bi-Weekly, Editor: C.S. Brown
  - The Richmond Planet- Richmond,Va June 21, 1890 (Volume 1:11)
  - The Freeman- Indianapolis, Indiana Dec 31, 1892 (Volume 1:12)
  - The Negro Advocate- Richmond, Va Sept 27, 1902 (Volume 1:13)
    Frequency: Bi-Weekly, Editor: The Negro Advocate Company
  - The New York Age- New York,NY 1921 (Volume 1:14)
    Frequency: Weekly, Editor: Fred R. Moore
  - Nashville Globe- Nashville,TN Aug 16, 1935 (Volume 1:15)
  - The Brunswick Beacon- Brunswick Co, Va Oct 1991, March-April 1990, July, OCt 1990, Sept-Nov 1989 (Volume 1:16)
    Frequency: Monthly, Editor: Jerome Bass
  - The Informant- Buckingham Co, Va April 1991 (Volume 1:17)
    Frequency: Monthly, Editor: Charles W. White
  - The Southside Virginia Star-Petersburg, Va, The Langstonian- Langston HS, Danville Va, The Liberator-New York June 1990, May 1993, April 1951, Jan 1949
    Frequency: Unknown Editor: Paul Bland, Frequency: Every 6 Weeks, Frequency: 1st Issue Editor: The Official Organ Of the Civil Rigths Congress